There are lots of good reasons
to try and follow a healthier diet—
you lose weight,
you feel good,
but the main reason?
To live a longer, happier,
more productive life.
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we answer what may sound
like a very unusual question:
can revitalizing blood with
blood transfusions slow aging?
In our first story,
we consider gruesome
experiments
that surgically attached old
animals to young ones
to show that there is something
in the blood that causes aging.
One of the major hallmarks
of aging
is the decline of regenerative
capacity of our tissues.
There are stem cells residing
in our muscles, for example,
that can leap into service
at the first sign of injury
to repair any damage.
Is the waning
of tissue renewing abilities
due to some intrinsic property
of aging stem cells
or a consequence of being
trapped in an aging body?
To find out, researchers grafted
the muscles of old rats
into young rats and vice-versa.
Inside the young rat,
even the weak atrophied muscles
of extremely old rats
at the end of their lives
regained their strength, volume,
and ability to regenerate.
They became young again,
so the capacity
was still there all along.
And young muscles in old rats
lost renewal capacity,
so it appeared to be something
about the surrounding milieu
rather than
inherent defects with age.
To see if the critical elements
were circulating
in the bloodstream,
old muscle stem cells
were cultured
in the blood of young animals.
This alone had
a rejuvenating effect,
suggesting that there may be
some sort of vitalizing factors
in youth that we lose as we age,
or inversely,
some repair-repressing component
that builds up.
Either way,
this may be good news,
because if we can find out
what those factors are,
we may be able to slow aging
or even reverse it.
Could more than just muscle
be restored?
What about the brain
and all the other organs?
To see the extent in which
circulating factors might play
in affecting aging,
researchers turned
to a macabre procedure
called parabiosis, from the
Greek para, meaning "next to,"
and bios, for "life."
It was an attempt
to recreate the phenomenon
of conjoined twins in a lab
by sewing animals together
to study the effects
of transmissible factors.
Conjoined twins are often
referred to as "Siamese twins,"
due to the notoriety of a 19th
century pair of Siamese-American
brothers joined at the chest.
The Blazek sisters are the
only conjoined twins on record
ever having given birth.
Josepha and Rosa Blazek
were quite literally
joined at the hip.
When Rosa got pregnant,
both of their breasts developed
and started lactating,
supporting the theory
we now know to be true today
that lactation is
regulated by hormones
that circulate in the blood.
So what about aging factors
circulating in the blood?
Surgically, researchers can
connect the skin, circulation,
muscle walls, body cavities,
and shoulder blade joints
of two animals.
Early attempts to graft
different species failed--
for example, mammals to birds
or a cat to a rat,
but in 1862,
a pioneering French scientist
was able to successfully pair
together two young rats.
The first heterochronic union--
hetero meaning "different,"
Chronos meaning "time"--
the first heterochronic union
was created in 1955
to answer the question:
What would happen if you bathed
the tissues of an old animal
in the blood of a young one?
The title of the paper was,
"Experimental Prolongation
of the Life Span."
Old rats hooked up to young rats
lived about 20 percent longer
than old rats
hooked up to one another.
Subsequent experiments showed
old mice coupled with young
became healthier, stronger,
and smarter.
Aged tissues in a number
of organs were rejuvenated,
including the brain, heart,
pancreas, skeleton, and muscles.
That doesn't necessarily mean
that aging was slowed, though.
Rather than some sort of
restorative bloodborne factor,
maybe the older animals
were just taking advantage
of the reserve organ capacity
in the younger animals,
like having an extra set
of youthful kidneys.
To see whether there's
some aging or anti-aging
transmissible element,
rather than sharing organs and
an entire circulatory system,
what about just getting
a transfusion of young blood?
After all,
as an American Aging Association
journal review concluded:
"The use of parabiosis in humans
is currently not performed
due to the surgical
complications
and resulting
undesirable lifestyle."
Ya think?
But getting a transfusion
of young blood would be easy.
Does it work?
We'll find out next.
Vampires 2.0?
The ethical quandaries
of young blood infusion
in the quest for eternal life.
In an episode of the TV series
Silicon Valley entitled,
"The Blood Boy,"
a tech guru hires
a young assistant
from whom to transfuse
pints of blood
in an attempt to slow down
his aging.
The restoration of youth
by bathing in or drinking
the blood of youth
is a centuries-old trope
dating back at least
to the futile attempt
of ailing Pope Innocent VIII,
who, in the 1490s,
failed to live up to his name
by apparently drinking the blood
of three ten-year-old boys,
who, though a bargain--
"costing only
one ducat apiece"--
died in the process.
Might there be something
to it, though?
Though young blood did
not have a significant impact
on lifespan, otherwise,
infusing the blood
of young animals into old
did have a rejuvenating effects
on multiple organs
similar to
full-blown parabiosis,
In fact, not only does the
infusion of young mouse blood
improve age-related cognitive
dysfunction in old mice,
young human blood,
taken from umbilical cords,
worked too,
in mice engineered to not reject
the foreign tissue.
This led
to ongoing clinical trials
offering weekly infusions
of blood products
from young donors
to patients
with mild to moderate
Alzheimer's disease.
But there may be
an easier way.
Yes, the injection of blood
from young mice into old
can improve memory
and learning,
suggesting there's some kind
of restorative youth factor,
but the injection of blood
from old mice into young
can worsen memory and learning,
suggesting that instead
there's some sort
of debilitating aging factor.
Or maybe the old blood
is just diluting
the revitalizing factor
in the young mouse,
or, for that matter,
maybe the young blood
is diluting
the debilitating factor
in the old mouse.
The fact that old blood
appears to make things worse
more than young blood
makes them better
suggests maybe the latter
is the case,
but you don't know,
until you put it to the test.
Ready for a mind-blowing shift
in perspective?
Instead of infusing young blood
into old mice,
researchers at UC Berkeley
just diluted
the blood of old mice
by siphoning off the plasma,
the liquid portion of the blood,
and essentially replacing
half of it with water.
If the regeneration seen
in heterochronic parabiosis
and blood transfusions
were due to some
fountain of youth factor
in young blood,
then nothing should happen,
right?
But if all the young blood
was doing
was diluting
some debilitating aging factor,
then the water should work
just as well,
and it did.
The rejuvenation in the liver
was similar to parabiosis
or transfusion,
and in the muscles and the brain
it was even better.
So, most if not all the benefits
could be replicated
by simple dilution,
including an improvement
in cognitive capacity.
That's good news,
since there's already
an FDA approved procedure
in use today known
as therapeutic plasma exchange.
It's usually used to filter out
toxins or autoimmune antibodies,
but why not try using it
to try to dilute old blood
to treat Alzheimer's disease?
And that's exactly what
researchers did.
Hundreds of Alzheimer's patients
were randomized to a therapeutic
plasma exchange procedure,
or a placebo (sham) procedure,
and though it didn't seem
to help those
with mild Alzheimer's disease,
those with moderate Alzheimer's
randomized to the real procedure
experienced about 60% less
cognitive and functional decline
over a period of 14 months.
This is in stark contrast
to mainstay treatments
for Alzheimer's
like the drug memantine
that can help with symptoms
but don't actually change
or alter
the course of the disease.
And the added advantage
over blood transfusions,
as a Director of an Institute
of Biomedical Ethics put it:
"There is something peculiar
about the old literally
feeding on the young."
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.